בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is י"ב, Yud Beis, it's
April 12th on the 12th day of the עומר. Omer. Everything is
aligned. Okay, so we pick up at the bottom of י"א עמוד
ב' Yud Aleph Amud Beis and we're in the middle of the
משנה mishna that speaks about that the כהן המשיח's Kohen HaMashiach status
specifically about the bringing the פר par ox when he sins based
on his פסק psak is only specifically when he is anointed with
the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. What,
in all other ways the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who when there's
no שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha and wears the special שמונה בגדים shmonah
begadim has exactly the same status? This is the one area of
difference. Anyway, and
now so we've been also talking about the use of the שמן
המשחה. shemen hamishcha. So it says the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha was
used to anoint the next כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, even if the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the next כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was the
son of the existing כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. And
but it was not used to anoint the son of a king
unless there was... unless the kingship was somehow disputed between the sons
and so on. And as I mentioned, there's like a double reason
why the oil is always used for a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
Number one, that even though there might be a preference for the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol for the son, fundamentally it is not a
ירושה. yerusha. Right, the idea of being a king is fundamentally a
sense of that this passes down, you know, from father to son
or from ruler to child or whatever in England, right? It's sort
of like בנות צלפחד, Bnos Tzelofchad, right? It goes to the daughters
if there are no sons. But anyway, but fundamentally the whole institution
is defined as a ירושה yerusha which we'll get to. So fundamentally,
you know, there's no need to do this because it's clear who
the next one is. Of course, you know, the question is let's
say there are multiple sons, so you would assume it goes to
the בכור bechor and so on which we'll get to, whereas the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not fundamentally a ירושה. yerusha. It's funny
because on the one hand הגמרא the Gemara says הכהן המשוח תחתיו
מבניו, HaKohen HaMashuach tachtav mibanav, the one who is anointed from his
sons, but of course it was talking about אהרן Aharon so the
sons constituted all the כהנים. kohanim. So how much... but so might
there is a preference maybe for the son, but fundamentally it's not
a ירושה. yerusha. And the other point is that the primary use
of the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha was to anoint the vessels of
the מקדש, Mikdash, of the משכן Mishkan and the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol and the כהנים kohanim were seen as amongst those vessels of
the משכן. Mishkan. And therefore, that's why the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha
is always used by a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol but only used
by a king in a case-time of dispute. You got a question
David? Okay, so let's pick up with now now unfortunately there's a
lot of... there was corruption. Right. Yes, yes. That's a whole other
discussion from מסכת יומא. Masechet Yoma. So now הגמרא the Gemara says
like this, אמר מר, Amar Mar, ואין מושחין, ve'ein moshchin, it starts
with the word מושחין, moshchin, it's about 20 lines from the bottom,
about 5 lines above where it says שמואל א' ט"ז Shmuel Aleph
tes-zayin on the side. Okay,
אמר מר ואין מושחין מלך בן מלך, Amar Mar ve'ein moshchin melech
ben melech, but you do not anoint a king the son of
a king. מנלן, Menalan, where do you know that from? רב אחא
בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov דכתיב diksiv the verse says למען
יאריך ימים על ממלכתו הוא ובניו בקרב ישראל Lema'an yaarich yamim al
mamlachto hu uvanav bekerev Yisrael because so that his kingship should go,
you know, be lengthened, he and his sons. The whole idea he
and his sons also on lengthened means that it passes down throughout
the generations, there's continuity. ירושה היא לכם, Yerusha hi lachem, it is
an inheritance. Okay, the fundamental institution of being a king. ומנלן דכי
איכא מחלוקת בעי משיחה, Umenalan dechi ika machlokes ba'ei meshicha, so where
do you know if there's... if it's disputed you need to anoint?
ולאו כל דבעי מלכא מוריש מלכותא לבניה Velav kol deba'ei malka moris
malchusa livenai and you can't just say the king can choose which
of his sons to give it to? Sort of like thinking about...
no, meaning but that's not sufficient, there needs to be an act
of משיחה. meshicha. Okay, but that's by the way interesting, right? It's...
meaning that's sort of invoking I think, you know, the whole story
about דוד המלך David HaMelech and giving it to שלמה Shlomo and
so on that even though there's an idea of ירושה, yerusha, it
sort of ties into בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, can you pick one
heir amongst the heirs, redistribute your ירושה yerusha as you see fit,
you know, as opposed to the idea of the בכור. bechor. So
it's pretty interesting, I mean obviously it's drawing on our own history,
but it assumes within the idea of ירושה yerusha the king should
have the choice to designate his heir. That's what it's starting by
assuming, which is the reality of דוד. David. But within there it
says, but why isn't that sufficient? Let him do that. How do
you know that if that's disputed you also need the שמן המשחה
shemen hamishcha and his designating of his heir does not suffice? So
רב פפא Rav Papa אמר קרא amar kra the verse says הוא
ובניו בקרב ישראל, Hu uvanav bekerev Yisrael, he and his sons in
the midst of Israel. בזמן ששלום בישראל קרינן ביה הוא ובניו Bizman
sheshalom beYisrael karinan bei hu uvanav when it's בקרב bekerev like we're
all, you know, good, close and feeling warm with one another so
בזמן ששלום בישראל קרינן ביה הוא ובניו bizman sheshalom beYisrael karinan bei
hu uvanav then it works like normal ירושה. yerusha. Yeah, exactly. So
then it means like ירושה, yerusha, then it's the simple issue of
again, interestingly, not just passing it on to the firstborn but designating,
but amongst your sons, that suffices. ואפילו בלא משיחה, Va'afillu belo meshicha,
even without משיחה. meshicha. Of course the point is that doesn't... It
doesn't tell you that when it is disputed that you that you
do משיחה, meshicha, or that משיחה meshicha maybe there's something else you
do. I mean obviously we're going to draw in a minute on
the history by by דוד David and שלמה, Shlomo, but it also
how do you know משיחה's meshicha allowed? משיחה meshicha is the שמן
המשחה, shemen hamishcha, it sanctifies. How do you know you're allowed to
use it for a non-מקדש mikdash purpose? So we'll see about that.
תנו, Tanu, we taught in ברייתא, braita, the ברייתא, braita, אף יהוא
בן נמשי לא נמשח אלא מפני מחלוקתו של יורם. af Yehu ben
Nimshi lo nimshach ela mipnei machlokto shel Yoram. יהוא Yehu also was
anointed because of the dispute with יורם. Yoram. ותיפוק ליה משום דרישון
הוא? veteipok lei mishum derishon hu? So why... so that's what the
ברייתא braita said, but I don't get it, says יהוא Yehu is
the was the oldest son, so you don't need, so it says
so you don't need the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. So it sounds
like if it's going to the בכור, bechor, maybe even if some
people contest it, the status of the בכור bechor is objectively, I
mean you know, not disputed, so you don't use the שמן המשחה.
shemen hamishcha. You deal with, I mean if people contest your throne
you gotta deal with it, but you don't use the שמן המשחה
shemen hamishcha to designate, sounds like. But if it's not the בכור,
bechor, then... so if it's not the בכור bechor and still nobody
is disputing it, the king has designated his heir and nobody is
disputing it, okay, you also don't need it. You only need it
when it's the combination of the two: the non-בכור bechor that the
king has designated and it's being disputed. That's what it seems. Anyway,
so it says so why יהוא Yehu did you need it? I
mean he was
the
בכור. bechor. So it says ותיפוק ליה משום דרישון הוא? veteipok lei
mishum derishon hu? That's what I just said. If it is the
natural heir, the בכור, bechor, you don't do it. If it's someone
who is designated, not the בכור, bechor, and it's disputed, that's when
you need it. That's what the גמרא Gemara is assuming. So it
says חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chasorei mechasra vehachi katani. Here's how you
have to read it. מלכי בית דוד משוחין. malchei beit David meshuchin.
מלכי בית דוד malchei beit David are anointed. מלכי ישראל אין משוחין.
malchei Yisrael ein meshuchin. Are not anointed. I don't think it's the
other way around. מנלן? Menalan? Well no because again it's you know
in some ways needed to give them status, but on the other
hand again it's the question: are you allowed to use it? It's
שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha and so on. So since fundamentally non-מלכי ישראל
malchei Yisrael are not really deserving to be king they don't have
the right to use it. Okay, well let's just give it a
time. Okay, מלכי ישראל אין משוחין. malchei Yisrael ein meshuchin. מנלן? Menalan?
Where's this from? אמר רב אמר קרא amar Rav amar kra קום
משחהו כי זה הוא. kum moshchehu ki zeh hu. Arise and anoint
him. This is by דוד David because this is the one. This
is what השם Hashem says to שמואל. Shmuel. זה טעון משיחה. zeh
taun meshicha. This one and presumably his descendants when necessary get get
get anointed, ואין אחר טעון משיחה ve'ein acher taun meshicha and none
others. Okay, and now once we have that we understand אף יהוא
בן נמשי לא נמשח אלא מפני
מחלוקתו של יורם. af Yehu ben Nimshi lo nimshach ela mipnei machlokto
shel Yoram. So even... even יהוא, Yehu, even though he was the
בכור, bechor, since it was מלכי ישראל, malchei Yisrael, therefore if the
parallel had happened by מלכי בית דוד malchei beit David you wouldn't
do משיחה. meshicha. Okay, but since it was מלכי ישראל malchei Yisrael
you did do משיחה meshicha in that case because it was disputed,
even though he was the בכור. bechor. So now the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, ומשום מחלוקתו של יורם בן אחאב נימשח בשמן? umishum
machlokto shel Yoram ben Achav nimshach beshemen? I don't get it, says
the גמרא. Gemara. This is שמן המשחה, shemen hamishcha, this is sanctified
oil. So if you say based on the precedent of דוד, David,
right, again, it's pretty interesting, right, because in the end, you know,
we don't... we didn't get from the פסוק pasuk about king that
you use the שמן. shemen. We didn't, you know, so we sort
of are really drawing on the דוד David example. So anyway, if
you say based on that, so based on that that gives us
not only tells us how to do it but it gives license
to do it because it's שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. But by the
מלכי ישראל, malchei Yisrael, if we don't have any license to do
it how can we do it even if it's necessary? So the
גמרא Gemara says כדאמר רב פפא באפרסמא דכיא, kedamar Rav Papa ba'afarsema
dachya, like רב פפא Rav Papa will say in a minute, we're
dealing just with, you know, with clean oil like fragrant oil. הכי
נמי באפרסמא דכיא. hachi nami ba'afarsema dachya. It means we used oil,
we didn't use the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. We used some special
fragrant oil that sort of evoked, you know, the idea of the
שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha but we didn't actually use the שמן המשחה.
shemen hamishcha. So sometimes you need to have a ritual to designate
who the king is, okay, and even if it's a, you know,
and therefore but if you don't have the license to do it,
it's not מלכי בית דוד, malchei beit David, you'll do some type
of a parallel and that's what you get. So even though he
was the בכור, bechor, because it was disputed, etc., but it wasn't
מלכי בית דוד, malchei beit David, therefore they did it that way.
But the real הלכה halacha of שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha according to
the גמרא Gemara seems to be two criteria... well, it has to
be מלכי בית דוד. malchei beit David. It's only when it's not
the בכור bechor and it's only when it's also not the בכור
bechor and disputed. That seems to be what the גמרא Gemara is
saying. Yes, there's a historical note from saying from two kings says
השם Hashem ordered אלישע Elisha to anoint יהוא. Yehu. Right. So it
looks like it came directly from השם. Hashem. Right, but on the
other... so you're saying why did we... why did we not use,
you know, the fact that it was commanded there to become a
precedent? Yeah, I don't know, it's a good question. I mean, yeah,
it's a good question, like why we use the דוד David as
a precedent but not the יהוא Yehu one. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says ואת יהואחז מפני יהויקים שהיה גדול ממנו שש שנים. v'es
Yehoachaz mipnei Yehoyakim she'haya gadol mimenu sheish shanim. So they also know
it back to מלכות בית דוד. malchus Beis Dovid. יהואחז Yehoachaz they
anointed because he was because יהויקים Yehoyakim was a possible competitor, because
יהויקים Yehoyakim was two years older but they did יהואחז Yehoachaz first.
Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute. ומי קשיש מיניה? umi
kashish minei? But was יהויקים Yehoyakim really older than יהואחז? Yehoachaz?
והכתיב, v'haksiv, it says ובני יאשיהו, uvnei Yoshiyahu, יאשיהו, Yoshiyahu, the sons
of יאשיהו, Yoshiyahu, הבכור יוחנן השני יהויקים. habechor Yochanan hasheini Yehoyakim. Okay,
so it seems like יהויקים Yehoyakim was only the second son. השלישי
צדקיהו והרביעי שלום. hashlishi Tzidkiyahu v'harevi'i Shalum. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabi
Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan says הוא שלום הוא צדקיהו. hu Shalum
hu Tzidkiyahu. So first of all, that's a little bizarre because he's
conflating two sons, צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu and שלום. Shalum. We'll worry about that
in a minute. But what we're going to focus on right now
is הוא יוחנן הוא יהואחז. hu Yochanan hu Yehoachaz. He said יוחנן
Yochanan is really יהואחז. Yehoachaz.
So according to רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, okay, the first son—it's interesting,
יוחנן, Yochanan, יוחנן, Yochanan, anyway—is יהואחז. Yehoachaz. So why did they need
to anoint יהואחז, Yehoachaz, who was מלכות בית דוד malchus Beis Dovid
and the בכור? bechor? The ברייתא Beraisa says that he was the
younger son, but רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan is saying he's the older
son. So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם יהויקים קשיש. l'olam Yehoyakim kashish.
No, no, no. Even within רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, יהויקים Yehoyakim was
the older son. But it says it was the second son. ומאי
בכור? umai bechor? What does it mean by calling יהואחז Yehoachaz the
בכור? bechor? בכור למלכות. bechor l'malchus. It really means that he was
king first. It's not talking about birth order, it's talking about the
heir order. Okay. So yes, he was the first heir, but because
he was not the first son, that's why he needed to be
anointed. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ומי מלכי
זוטרי מקמי קשישי? umi malchi zutrei mikamei kashishei? Is it really true
that the younger one can be a king before the older one?
והכתיב v'haksiv ואת הממלכה נתן ליהורם כי הוא הבכור. v'es hamamlacha nasan
l'Yehoram ki hu habechor. So he gave the ממלכה, mamlacha, he gave
it to יהורם Yehoram because he was the eldest. Okay. So, you
know, so it sounds like only that he's the eldest son is
deserving and able to be the king. So the גמרא Gemara
says יהורם ממלא מקום אבותיו הוה יהויקים לא ממלא מקום אבותיו הוה.
Yehoram memalei makom avosav hava Yehoyakim lo memalei makom avosav hava. No.
If you are the oldest and you're fitting to be king, then
like again,
then you get it automatically. But if there's a more deserving candidate,
like you know, all things being equal, the בכור bechor gets it.
But you know, but if there's a more deserving candidate, one who
is like, you know, maybe clearly more deserving or a little bit
more deserving, anyway, so then
it can go to a younger son. Okay.
שלמה Shlomo wasn't—שלמה Shlomo wasn't the oldest? Exactly, exactly. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute. אמר מר amar mar הוא שלום הוא צדקיהו
hu Shalum hu Tzidkiyahu הוא יוחנן הוא יהואחז. hu Yochanan hu Yehoachaz.
והא חד חד קחשיב. v'ha chad chad kachashiv. How can you say
שלום Shalum and צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu are the same? The פסוק pasuk lists
them as two separate sons. The third is צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, the fourth
is שלום. Shalum. דכתיב השלישי הרביעי. d'chsiv hashlishi hareyvi'i. מאי שלישי שלישי
לבנים מאי רביעי רביעי למלכות. mai shlishi shlishi l'banim mai revi'i revi'i
l'malchus. Obviously, it's not a פשט pshat when you get to a
פסוק. pasuk. I have no idea. Anyway, it means the third son
in the birth order but the fourth son in the heir order.
דמעיקרא, d'meikra, so who was in who was in the middle? מלך
יהואחז ולבסוף יהויקים. malach Yehoachaz u'l'vasof Yehoyakim.
Because in the פסוקים psukim we've been talking about as a younger
son and but he was first, יהויקים Yehoyakim was the second son
and the second you know was the way the גמרא Gemara is
constructing it, the older son but the second to get the מלכות.
malchus. ולבסוף יכניה. u'l'vasof Yechanya.
But before you got to צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, what's not mentioned in the
פסוק pasuk is יכניה. Yechanya. ולבסוף צדקיהו. u'l'vasof Tzidkiyahu.
And finally צדקיהו. Tzidkiyahu. Okay, fine. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. הוא שלום
הוא צדקיהו ולמה נקרא שמו שלום שהיה משולם במעשיו, hu Shalum hu
Tzidkiyahu v'lama nikra shemo Shalum shehaya mishulam b'ma'asav, because he was like
a righteous person. איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, some say שלום ששלמה מלכות
בית דוד בימיו. Shalum sheshalma malchus beis Dovid b'yamav. A slightly different
connotation. He was the last of the kings of בית דוד. beis
Dovid. So not שלום Shalum as peace but as complete, you know,
he was the end, the final one. Okay. ומה שמו? u'mah shemo?
What was his actual name? מתניה שמו. Masanya shemo. His name was
מתניה. Masanya. שנאמר וימלך מלך בבל את מתניה דודו תחתיו ויסב את
שמו צדקיהו. she'ne'emar v'yamlech melech Bavel es Masanya dodo tachtav vayasov es
shemo Tzidkiyahu. And he gave him the name מתניה, Masanya, the uncle—not
his uncle, the uncle of the previous
king—תחתיו tachtav and he gave his name to be צדקיהו. Tzidkiyahu. Okay.
אמר ליה יה יצדיק עליך את הדין. amar lei Ya yatzdik alecha
es hadin. God should mete out justice against you. צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu sounds
like a nice name, you know, righteous of God. But here he's
saying no, God should mete out justice against you אם תמרוד בי
im timrod bi if you rebel against me like the previous kings
did.
וכתיב, v'chsiv, and it says ויביאהו בבלה. vayevi'eihu Bavelah. וכתיב וגם במלך
נבוכדנצר מרד. v'chsiv v'gam b'melech Nevuchadnetzar marad. Guess what, that's exactly what
happened. אשר השביעו באלהים, asher hishbi'o b'Elohim, even though he had been
foresworn, taken oath. Okay, now, so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara basically
says that a king if it's a natural ירושה yerusha don't need
שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. If it is not the eldest son, it's
a little bit unclear—do you need two criteria, not the eldest son
plus the other sons are actively contesting it, or are we just
saying anytime it's not the eldest son it's implicitly contested and therefore
you need it? I think I was describing it before as like
two criteria. I think it is a little vague whether it's sort
of saying as long as it's not the oldest son is it
implicitly contested, but anyway, but certainly the cases when it's not the
oldest son when you need the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. יהואחז במלכי
ישראל. Yehoachaz b'malchei Yisrael. יהוא Yehu was from מלכות ישראל, Malchut Yisrael,
right. So, I was going back to what was before. No, let's
not go back. We have way too much גמרא Gemara to cover.
Okay, it's just symbolic, it doesn't have any actual. Well, what do
you mean it's just symbolic?
It's it's it's
you could pass on the king without the oil. No, no, I
mean I think it's an interesting question which we're going to get
to, which is, which is in this case when it's contested and
we say that we need the שמן המשחה, Shemen HaMishcha, what are
you going to do when you don't have the שמן המשחה, Shemen
HaMishcha, which is exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going to turn
to, okay? But even if there's other ways to create substitutes, it
doesn't mean that it's not the primary ritual, and it's and it's
something that you need it's you're using something that's sanctified, so clearly
that's something that, you know, according to the way the גמרא Gemara
understands it, you're obligated to do and you have license to do.
That doesn't mean that if you don't have it that you can't
find some substitute, which is what we're going to get to. ומי
הוי שמן המשחה? Umi havei Shemen HaMishcha? Was there actually שמן המשחה
Shemen HaMishcha in the time of, you know, these later kings, in
יהואחז Yehoachaz and so on? והתניא, Vehatanya, turned in a ברייתא, Baraita,
top of י"ב עמוד א', Yud Bet Amud Aleph, משנגנז ארון, Mishenignaz
Aron, from the time that the ארון Aron was hidden, which we're
going to say was going to be in the time of יאשיהו,
Yoshiyahu, נגנז שמן המשחה, nignaz Shemen HaMishcha, the שמן המשחה Shemen HaMishcha
was hidden with it, וצנצנת המן, vetsintsenet haman, and the, you know,
the sort of container of מן, Man, ומקלו של אהרן, umaklo shel
Aharon, and the stick of אהרן Aharon because the מן Man and
the staff were put together with the ארון, Aron, it says in
the פסוקים, Psukim, put them next to the
ארון. Aron. שקדיה ופרחיה, Shkedaia uprachaya, interesting that it feels it wants
to mention that, you know, the miracle that was done with it
that it blossomed. Okay,
וארגז ששלחו פלשתים דורון לישראל, ve'argaz sheshalschu Plishtim doron leYisrael, and also
what was buried was the box was the chest that was sent
by the פלשתים Plishtim to Israel. שנאמר, Shene'emar, it says, ואת כלי
הזהב אשר השבותם לו אשם, ve'et klei hazahav asher heshivotem lo asham,
this was what the פלשתים Plishtim priests said to the, you know,
the heads of the פלשתים, Plishtim, when they were all being smitten
because they had seized the ארון Aron and they had to return
the ארון Aron and they said well you can't just send it
back, you got to send it back with some type of a
gift to God and that would be an atonement for your sin,
so they sent back all of these gold things, interesting what the
gold things were fashioned like anyway. So it says, and all the
gold vessels asher, so these are now the פלשתים Plishtim priests talking
to them, ואת כלי הזהב אשר השבותם לו אשם, ve'et klei hazahav
asher heshivotem lo asham, and those golden vessels which you're going to
turn to it as a type of a sin offering, תשימו בארגז
מצדו, tasimu ba'argaz mitsido, put in a chest alongside the ארון. Aron.
ושלחתם אתו והלך, Veshalachtem oto vehalach, and you shall send it to
him to God their God and it will go. Now it's very
interesting, since they said מצדו, mitsido, so since the פלשתים Plishtim priests
said that the box has to be near the ארון, Aron, when
it was being transported, that indicates that the box was always kept
near the ארון Aron and even when it was in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and even when it was hidden, which is fascinating.
Sounds like it was crowded in there. Yeah, okay, but I'm just
shocked that we go by the by what the פלשתים Plishtim priests
said. Okay, ומי גנזו, Umi ganzo, now who was the one that
actually hid it? יאשיהו מלך יהודה גנזו, Yoshiyahu Melech Yehuda ganzo, he
hid it. שראה שכתוב בתורה יולך ה' אותך ואת מלכך אשר תקים
עליך אל גוי אשר לא ידעת, Shera'ah shakatuv baTorah yolech Hashem otcha
ve'et malchecha asher takim alecha el goy asher lo yadata, that you
you and your king will be taken to a foreign nation. So
he saw that, you know, he anticipated the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
was going to be destroyed, the kings were going to be taken
to בבל Bavel and he did not want the ארון Aron to
fall into their hands, which allows us to have the Steven Spielberg
movie of Raiders of the Lost Ark. Okay,
צוה וגנזם, tsiva uganzam, so he commanded it and it was hidden.
שנאמר ויאמר ללוים המבינים לכל ישראל הקדושים לה' תנו את ארון הקודש
בבית אשר בנה שלמה בן דויד מלך ישראל אין לכם משא בכתף
עתה עבדו את ה' אלהיכם ואת עמו ישראל, Shene'emar vayomer laleviyim hamevinim
lechol Yisrael hakadoshim l'Hashem tnu et aron hakodesh babayit asher bana Shlomo
ben David Melech Yisrael ein lachem masa bakatef ata ivdu et Hashem
Elokeichem ve'et amo Yisrael, and he said to the Levites who understood
to all of Israel holy to God, put the holy ark in
the house that Solomon the son of David king of Israel built,
you no longer have a burden on the
shoulder, now serve the Lord your God and His people Israel. Now
where does it sound like he hid it? Just sounds like he
put it into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Wasn't it there already?
So well A, it was there already. B, so what does it
mean now you don't carry it with a כתף? katef? It's not
like they crossed the Jordan and they had been moving it. So
the גמרא Gemara interprets it to mean if it gets taken captive
and brought into בבל, Bavel, you will never have an opportunity to
bring it back on your shoulders like it was initially brought from
the wilderness into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So since it will never
be able to be transported back, you better hide it now. That's
how the גמרא Gemara reads it.
ואמר רבי אלעזר, ve'amar Rabbi Elazar, אתיא שם שם אתיא משמרת משמרת
אתיא דורות דורות. Asya sham sham, asya mishmeret mishmeret, asya dorot dorot.
Based on linked words, by the ארון Aron it says ונועדתי לך
שם, venoadeti lecha sham, I'll meet with you there. וכתיב Vechativ by
the מן Man it says ותן שמה מלא העמר מן. veten shama
melo ha'omer Man. So if the ארון Aron was put away, the
מן Man was. And it says by the
מן Man לפני ה' למשמרת לדורותיכם. lifnei Hashem lemishmeret ledoroteichem. And it
says by the שמן המשחה Shemen HaMishcha יהיה זה לי לדורותיכם. yihyeh
zeh li ledoroteichem. So if the מן Man was put away, the
שמן המשחה Shemen HaMishcha was put away. And it says by אהרן
Aaron's staff,
it says where is
it... it says by the מן Man למשמרת לדורותיכם lemishmeret ledoroteichem and
by אהרן Aaron's staff it says למשמרת לאות. lemishmeret le'ot. So all
those links tell you it got put away and of course the
chest that the פלשתים Plishtim sent, it's because the פלשתים Plishtim priests
said that it should be next to the ארון, Aron, so there
you go. I love that. Anyway, okay, אמר רב. amar Rav. אמר
רב פפא. Amar Rav Papa. Anyway, so that's our question: how did
they anoint these final kings of מלכי ישראל Malchei Yisrael בית דוד
Beit David if there was no longer the שמן המשחה? Shemen HaMishcha?
When Josiah גנז ganaz the ארון הקודש, Aron HaKodesh, בודאי, bevadai, it
means hide it somewhere in the house. Hide it somewhere in the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right, exactly. That's why you know the גמרא
Gemara talks about they sort of when they were cleaning out once,
they thought they found where it was hidden. Anyway, אמר רב פפא,
Amar Rav Papa, but yes, that's an important point. It's hidden somewhere
on the grounds of the Temple Mount. אמר רב פפא באפס מדחיא,
Amar Rav Papa b'afas madachei, so here Rav Papa said it, fine.
When they don't have that option, you're dealing with מלכי ישראל, Malchei
Yisrael, you're dealing with מלכי בית דוד, Malchei Beit David, but it's
after the שמן shemen has been hidden, then you do some substitute
ritual, okay, 'cause you need some ritual, right? So you but but
but nevertheless, the real הלכה halacha is, so yes, it was pointed
out it's possible to be king without it, okay, but nevertheless, when
it's avail you know when it's available you're obligated to do it,
allowed to do it, obligated to do it, you have special and
so on, and that's how you do it. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. כיצד מושחין את המלכים? Keitzad moshchin et hamelachim? How do you
actually do the act of anointing? כמין נזר, K'min nezer, like a
crown, which presumably means you circle around the head like that, you
know, like you draw a crown around it. Okay. Are you using
your finger or are you actually just pouring the oil? No,
no, there's going to be pouring on the top, יציקה, yetzika, and
then משיחה meshicha is actually taking oil on the finger and doing
and sort of put the oil on the top.
That's interesting, maybe, but I thought it was going back to the
original vessel. Either way, taking oil and doing something with it. Okay.
So כמין נזר, k'min nezer, obviously to designate kingship, okay, ואת
הכהנים כמין כי, v'et hakohanim k'min chi, and by הכהנים kohanim like
a כי. chi. So מאי כמין כי? mai k'min chi? אמר רב
מנשיא בר גדא כמין כף יוני, Amar Rav Menashia bar Gadda k'min
chaf yevani, like a Greek כף. chaf. Now I think a Greek
Chi is an X, right? So yeah, so I think it's an
X, but רש"י Rashi says it's like a חית chet and רש"י
Rashi says if I understand רש"י Rashi correct, you start from between
the eyes and you go straight up and straight over the head
and back, so it's like an arch like that. That's why רש"י
Rashi reads it, sort of like a חית, chet, as if you
were to put a חית chet over my head, you know what
I mean? Anyway, okay, that's why but a כי chi is really
an X.
Okay.
תני חדא בתחלה מותקין שמן על ראשו, Tani chada batchila motzkin shemen
al rosho, first you pour the oil on the head, ואחר כך
נותנין לו שמן בין ריסי עיניו, v'achar kach notnin lo shemen bein
risei einav, and then between his you know his eyebrows. So either
between his eyebrows and like that, or between his eyebrows and an
X or the and so on.
ותניא אידך, V'tanya idach, and another's teach, בתחלה נותנין לו שמן בין
ריסי עיניו, batchila notnin lo shemen bein risei einav, no you start
by this application of the oil between the eyebrows and making the
כי chi or making whatever, ואחר כך
מותקין לו שמן על ראשו, v'achar kach motzkin lo shemen al rosho,
and then you pour it on the head. So תנאי תנאי היא,
Tannai Tannai hi, so it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. איכא דאמרי
משיחה עדיפא, Ikka d'amri meshicha adifa, some say the assumption is whichever
one you do first is the more important one, some say the
more important is the act of anointing which is drawing like the
שמן המשחה Shemen HaMishcha drawing the X on the you know between
the eyes or whatever you're doing with the
כי. chi. ואיכא דאמרי אידך יציקה עדיפא, V'ikka d'amri idach yetzika adifa,
the pouring is more important. מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר יציקה עדיפא? Mai
taama d'man d'amar yetzika adifa? דכתיב ויצק משמן המשחה על ראש אהרן—he
d'chtiv vayitzok mishmen hamishcha al rosh Aharon poured from the שמן המשחה
Shemen HaMishcha on Aaron's head—וימשח אתו—and vayimshach oto afterwards he anointed him,
seeing that as a separate act—לקדשו. l'kadsho. So by the way, it's
funny the use of the word word חשיבא, chashiva, עדיפא adifa is
better. 'Cause you could have still said, as Michael points out, you
know, it's still שמן המשחה Shemen HaMishcha and the end of the
פסוק pasuk is וימשח אתו לקדשו, vayimshach oto l'kadsho,
it still thinks seems that the ultimate thing that is being done
is the act of משיחה. meshicha. So even if you start by
pouring the oil on the head, it doesn't mean it's the more
important one, it just means it comes first. Okay? But nevertheless, that's
one appro but but nevertheless the פסוק pasuk liter at least minimally
does indicate that it comes first. Okay, ומאן דאמר משיחה עדיפא, u'man
d'amar meshicha adifa, the one who says משיחה meshicha is more important
and comes first, מאי טעמא? mai taama? כסבר שכן אתה מוצא אצל
כלי שרת, Kasavar sheken ata motzei etzlei k'lei shareit, because similar to
Michael's point, the כלי שרת k'lei shareit didn't get oil poured on
their head, they just got משיחה. meshicha. Okay? And therefore משיחה meshicha
clearly is the key act. והכתיב ויצק ובסוף וימשח? Veha chtiv vayitzok
v'basof vayimshach? Fine, you could say it's more important, but but the
פסוק pasuk indicates that it comes first, that at least יציקה yetzika
comes first, whichever is more important, at least the pouring on the
on the head comes first. So the גמרא Gemara says
הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: מאי טעם ויצק? mai taam vayitzok? משום דוימשח.
mishum d'vayimshach. Because you had already anointed. Again, a very hard read
of the פסוק. pasuk. ויצק שמן על ראשו Vayitzok shemen al rosho
given that he had already וימשח אתו לקדשו, vayimshach oto l'kadsho, he
had already done the משיחה. meshicha. Very hard read of the פסוק,
pasuk, and it's it's interesting why the גמרא Gemara feels that just
because you say it's more important means it has to come first.
Okay? But anyway, the debate is which one is more first comes
first, which is being interpreted as which one is more important. Okay.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: כשמן הטוב ירד על הזקן זקן אהרן, k'shemen
hatov yored al hazakan zakan Aharon, like the good oil which comes
down on the beard, the beard of Aaron, very interesting פסוק pasuk
in תהלים. Tehillim. Speaks about oil there held in the beard of
Aaron. So obviously evoking the idea of anointing Aaron with the שמן
המשחה. Shemen HaMishcha.
So it says כמין שני טפי מרגליות היו תלויות לאהרן בזקנו, k'min
shenei tipei margaliyot hayu teluyot l'Aharon bizkano, like he had like two
pearl drops of oil like suspended to Aaron in his beard. on
the tip of his beard. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, תנא
כשהוא מספר, tana k'shehu mesaper, when he was talking to somebody, ועולות
ויושבות לו בעיקר זקנו, v'oloyt v'yoshvot lo b'ikar zikno, they would the
drops of oil would rise up and go like to the root
of the hairs, so they wouldn't I guess drip off as you're
talking, okay, but also I think probably to indicate, you know, you're
talking with the mouth, so sort of the sanctity of the words
that are coming out, you know, it's sort of rising up and
it's being close to the mouth, I think is another way of
understanding it. Okay. ועל דבר זה היה משה דואג, V'al davar zeh
haya Moshe doeg, the fact that this oil was sort of dripping
and still in Aaron's beard after he had been anointed, Moshe was
worried about this. אמר שמא חס ושלום מעלתי בשמן המשחה. Amar shema
chas v'shalom ma'alti b'shemen hamishchah. Maybe God forbid I misused the שמן
המשחה. shemen hamishchah. Now Rashi says it's because he says maybe when
I was anointing Aaron and the sons, I accidentally touched it and
got some benefit, but then it doesn't exactly explain the how it's
connected to the extra drops on Aaron's beard. You know, maybe the
point is, well, maybe if it was so much, maybe I used
an excessive amount. But then, you know, anyway, יצתה בת קול ואמרה,
yatza bas kol v'amrah, a heavenly voice came out and said no,
כשמן הטוב היורד על הזקן זקן אהרן, k'shemen hatov hayored al hazakan
zakan Aharon, no, it's the good oil, don't worry, this is the
way it should be. Okay, and then the פסוק pasuk continues, כטל
חרמון, k'tal Chermon, like the dew of the Chermon. מה טל חרמון
אין בו מעילה, Mah tal Chermon ein bo me'ilah, and the same
way there's no מעילה me'ilah with dew, אף שמן המשחה שבזקן אהרן
אין בו מעילה, af shemen hamishchah shebizkan Aharon ein bo me'ilah, there's
also no מעילה me'ilah here, don't worry. Okay, probably it's like נעשית
מצותו, na'asis mitzvaso, anyway after you're done, the מצוה mitzvah is done
with it, so there's no longer מעילה. me'ilah. What do you mean
that there are two drops in a? I don't know, I am
sure the Kabbalist can do a lot with it, I I I
I just do not have any anything profound to say. I'm willing
to accept any any legitimate suggestion. ועדיין היה אהרן דואג, V'adayin haya
Aharon doeg, Aaron was still was still anxious. Still Aaron himself was
was concerned. אמר שמא משה לא מעל אבל אני מעלתי, Amar shema
Moshe lo ma'al aval ani ma'alti, maybe I was מעל, ma'al, maybe
you know too much of it fell on me and I got
benefit from it, יצתה בת קול ואמרה לו הנה מה טוב ומה
נעים שבת אחים גם יחד. yatza bas kol v'amrah lo hineh mah
tov u'mah naim shevet achim gam yachad. We can start we can
break out in song. מה משה לא מעל אף אתה לא מעלת.
Mah Moshe lo ma'al af atah lo ma'alta.
All right, there's I'm sure a lot of beautiful things you can
do with this story, I just it's all the same פרק perek
of תהילים. Tehillim. Okay, my anyway my imagination muscle was not working
last night when I was preparing the דף, daf, so I don't
have anything that creative right now to say. תנו רבנן, Tano rabbanan,
אין מושחין את המלכים אלא על המעיין, ein moshchin es ham'lachim ela
al hamayan, when you do the anointing of kings, which now as
we know is only when in exceptional cases, not all the time,
you do it
by a by a well, by like a flowing water, by you
know by a spring. Right. כדי שתמשך מלכותם, k'dei shetimshach malchusam, the
the symbolism is the same way the water is not stationary, it's
not a cistern, but it's like coming alive from the ground, obviously
water represents life, you know prosperity, so similarly, you know, their kingship
should go for you know for many years. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, and be
and be successful. שנאמר ויאמר המלך להם קחו עמכם את עבדי אדוניכם,
She'ne'emar vayomer hamelech lahem k'chu imachem es avdei adoneichem, so this is
now talking about Shlomo, the king said take from your the servants
of your masters והורדתם אתו אל גיחון, v'horadetem oso el Gichon, bring
him to the Gichon valley, you know where they had the spring
and that's where you should anoint him. אמר רבי אמי והאי מאן
דבעי למידע אי מסיק שתיה אילו. Amar Rabbi Ami v'hai man d'ba'e
leida im masik shateh lei lo. Now here we're going to get
to now that we're talking about symbolism, this is one of the
core places in the גמרא Gemara where it talks about the significance
about using doing symbolic actions and about you know the special foods
on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah whatever, so then we're going to totally
digress, but it's talking about the power of symbolic actions. Okay, so
somebody who wants to know but but if you want to know
אי מסיק שתיה אילו, im masik shateh lei lo, if your like
you know it's going to be a successful year or not, נייתי
שרגא בעשרה יומי דבין ראש השנה ליום הכיפורים, neisei shraga b'asar yomei
d'vein Rosh Hashanah l'Yom haKippurim, light a candle in the ten days
between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום הכיפורים, Yom haKippurim, I gotta
give you a little secret, there are not ten days between ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום הכיפורים, Yom haKippurim, I guess if you
include the endpoints. Okay anyway, בביתא דלא נשיב זיקא, b'veisa d'lo nashiv
zika,
light it in a house where there's no where there's no wind,
אי משיך נהוריה, im mashich nehorei,
and if the light continues to burn like to the bottom of
the candle, okay it burns for a long time, then נידע דמסיק
שתיה, neida d'masik shateh, you'll know you'll have a successful year. ומאן
דבעי למעבד עיסקא, U'man d'ba'e l'meved b'iska,
so this is less of a doing things of symbolic significance and
more trying to you know it's one thing you do a סימן
siman that it should be a good sign you know and have
have a positive impact on what's going to come. It's another thing
that you look at certain things and you try to you know
determine the future. Okay, so it's not so anyway and that becomes
very interesting question, since when is any of this allowed? Like are
we not supposed to לא תנחשו ולא תעוננו, lo senachashu v'lo te'onenu,
we're not supposed to do things, you know, so this leads to
important like halakhic discussions, what are the exact parameters of not trying
to forecast the future? Okay, so if you want to go ahead
and be and do some business deal or business investment ובעי למידע
אי מצלח ליה לא מצלח, u'ba'e leimeida im matzlach lei lo matzlach,
and you want to know if it'll be successful or not, should
I invest in Google or not? So or right now should I
take should I should I sell all my Facebook stocks right now?
Okay, לירבי תרנגולא, lei'rbi tarnagola, so so raise... Raise a chicken. אי
שמין ושפיר, i shamin vshafir, if it gets nice and fatty and
good, then מצלח, matzlach, then you'll know that chicken will symbolically represent
your investment and therefore if it turns out like a good chicken
you know it'll be a good investment. Okay. האי מאן דבעי למיפק
לאורחא hai man dbaye lmiphak lorcha if you want to go on
a journey, ובעי למידע אי חזר ואתי לביתי לא, ubaye lmeida i
chazar vati lbaytei lo, like when they would go on journeys they
never knew if they would come home, right? There was always, they
would travel in caravans and ships or whatever, you never know if
you're going to survive and come home. So you want to know
if you'll make it back home. ניקום בביתא דחברא, nikum bbayta dchavra,
go to your friend's house. אי חזי בבבואה דבבואה, i chazi bbavua
dbavua,
and if you see a shadow of a shadow or
a reflection of a reflection, I'm sorry, reflection of a reflection, לידע
דהדר ואתי לביתיה, leida dhadar vati lbaytei, then you'll know that you'll
return and come to your house. So maybe being in your friend's
house symbolizes being away and seeing a reflection of a reflection means
that you'll come back like there will be anyway. But then the
גמרא Gemara says but in this last one ולאו מילתא היא, vlav
milsa hi, that's really not a thing.
דילמא חלשא דעתיה ומיסתרא מזליה, dilma chalsha daatei umistara mazlei, maybe you'll
go despondent and it actually makes things worse. So the way רש"י
Rashi says it is this is not a
100% tested predictor, imagine that. And therefore you'll do it and you
won't see the reflection of the
reflection and really you would have otherwise returned. But since this predictor
isn't so good, you'll see this and you'll think you won't return
and that actually will make you not return because then you'll be
despondent and you won't be able to face up to the adversity.
So here I think it's interesting the גמרא Gemara is sort of
reflecting on oh that was
unintentional anyway about the fact about how these things play out psychologically,
right? Like I mean if you think that things are going to
be good sometimes they do become like self-fulfilling prophecies that gives you
a certain attitude and a certain
sense, no like I knew I saw the סימן siman it was
going to be good and you try extra hard and you have
that belief and if you think it's not going to be good
that also can sometimes become a self-fulfilling prophecy. So the גמרא Gemara
isn't exactly saying that but it is acknowledging the role of how
these impact your frame of mind and how your frame of mind
therefore impacts the outcome is a piece of what's going on here.
Okay and now the גמרא Gemara says so that's trying to predict
the future. But now the גמרא Gemara says more about doing a
סימן siman that will sort of be a good sign for the
future. אמר אביי השתא דאמרת סימנא מילתא היא, amar Abaye hashta damart
simana milsa hi,
now that you say that doing things that are symbolic
has some substance, has some meaning, so לעולם יהא רגיל למיחזי בריש
שתא, leolam yehei ragil lmechezei breish shata,
you should always try, here it says to see on Rosh Hashanah,
but I think other גרסאות girsas have למיכל. lmeichal. Yes, some למיכל,
lmeichal, you should always try to eat on Rosh Hashanah קרא ורוביא
כרתי וסילקי ותמרי. kara vrubya karsi vsilki vtamrei. So apparently what are
these various things?
קרא kara is a gourd, right קרא kara is a gourd. רוביא
rubya is I think what's רוביא? rubya? Is it beets? What does
it say there? Fenugreek. Oh, fenugreek, our famous fenugreek. כרתי karsi is
leek. סילקי silka is a
beet. Yeah, beet. ותמרי vtamrei and dates. So why them? So רש"י
Rashi says those are things that ripen quickly in the year so
therefore they're somehow a symbol of something that's rich, it's sort of
like or something that's
successful, the whole idea that we talk about לראש ולא לזנב, lrosh
vlo lzanav, those types of things. They used to joke you take
some celery and a half a raisin and a piece of lettuce
and you say let us have a raisin celery. So anyway, but
anyway, but the גמרא Gemara here is not playing with the words,
it's sort of just saying that these are things that are
symbolically indicate success.
Okay. אמר להו רב משרשיא לבניו, amar lehu Rav Mesharshia livneiv, Rav
Mesharshia said to his
sons, כי בעיתו מעלי למיגמרי קמי רבייכו, ki baitu meaili lmigmarei kammai
rabbeichu, when you want to go learn before your רבי rebbe and
the keyword here is למיגמרי, lmigmarei, גמרא, Gemara, okay? So your גירסו
מתניתא girsu matnita first learn the text, right? The גמרא Gemara is
like the analysis of the text.
Oh look at this, he's talking in the plural.
Oh that's a good point, he's talking in the plural. Anyway, so
it's אמר להו, amar lehu, right, so it's לבני, livnei, some of
the גרסאות girsas have לבני livnei not לבריה, lvray, so it means
to his sons, that's correct. Okay, so he said to his sons,
when you want to go and learn, so you're going to learn,
you're going to sort of be an analysis of the text, so
you first have to have that text really under your belt. You
really have to master the משנה, Mishnah, the core text that now
you're going to be spending your time discussing and analyzing. So come
prepared. גירסו מתניתא girsu matnita first be גורס goreis which is just
like the memorization of the text, the משנה, Mishnah, the ברייתא, Baraisa,
ועלו לקמי רבייכו valu lkammai rabbeichu and then go in front of
your רבי. rebbe. וכי יתביתו קמיה vchi yasvitu kammai and when you're
sitting in front of him, חזו לפומיה, chazu lpumei, you should try
to see his mouth as he's talking. It evokes that idea of
like the mouth of אהרן Aharon when the oil went up, right
that דכתיב dechsiv ועיניך רואות את מוריך, ve'einecha ro'os es morecha, you
should see your רבי. rebbe. So that's you know, there's גמרות gemaras
about that that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir said I saw the back
of my רבי, rebbe, if I'd seen the front, I would have
been that much greater. So you could sort of talk about that
pedagogically, you know, you see the facial expressions, you see more about
what's trying to be communicated, you know, not just symbolically, you also
create a more emotional connection, you're inspired, you know, maybe if you
see the visage of your רבי rebbe or, you know, if he
holds himself in a certain way, but also there's something here about
just looking at the lips, you know, that seem to be also
symbolic, not just sort of pedagogic or inspirational. Yes. You said we
call it תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-be-al peh. That's a nice point
too. It is all about the oral tradition. So that sense of
that continuity, that's a very good point, exactly.
וכי גרסיתו, ve-chi garsisu, and when you so that's point number one,
which gets back to those themes. And now וכי גרסיתו ve-chi garsisu
when you are before you went in, you're spending your time memorizing
the material, גרסו על נהרא. girsu al nahara. Go to the river
and and that's where you should be spending your time memorizing. על
נהרא דמיא דכי היכי דמשכי מיא משכי שמעתייכו al nahara de-maya de-chi
hachi de-mashkin maya mashkin shamaisaikhu on a river of water that the
same way the water is flowing, you similarly, you know, your teaching
should also be flowing, that obviously evokes that earlier theme about the
anointing of kings. Okay. וסיבלא אקיקלי דמתא מחסיא ve-sivla kikli de-masa machasia
now so that's sort of the symbolism, and now we're going to
sort of a little bit on a different point, ויתיבו אקיקלי דמתא
מחסיא ve-isivu a-kikli de-masa machasia would be better to sit on the
dunghill or on the garbage heaps of מתא מחסיא Masa Machasia which
is a city filled with, you know, Torah scholars, ולא תיתבו אפדני
דפומבדיתא velo sivu apadani de-pumbedisa
and not sit in some sort of like, you know, nice throne
in Pumbedisa because because Pumbedisa did was not as rich of a
of a city in Torah. What? אפדני. apadani.
Right. טב גלדנא סריא. tav galdana sarya. What? אפדני. apadani. אפדני apadani
I think is like a throne.
Okay. So
טב גלדנא סריא tav galdana sarya דמתא de-masa now we'll read it
without the brackets. Rashi did not seem to have the brackets. Better
is a a day old fish מכותחא דרמי כיפי mi-kucha de-rami kifi
from a powerful כותחא kutach which was this sort of like a
a yogurt crouton dip or whatever that's so strong that it could
break rocks. Nevertheless health-wise, you know, it might be very tasty and
powerful and pungent, but health-wise a slightly rotting fish is better. The
גמרא gemara actually thought that fish right before it went bad is
actually is when it's healthiest.
Okay. רמה קרני בה', rama karni belohai, so my horn is lifted
up to my God, רמה קרני ולא רמה פכי. rama karni velo
rama pachi. My horn but not my like פך, pach, my you
know not my uh what what do you call a פך pach
like a little what? A pitcher like a פך שמן, pach shemen,
a little
there's a word for
that anyway. What? A flask.
A flask. Okay. Anyway so my you know my horn and not
my flask. Um a cruse is what the word I was looking
for.
דוד ושלמה שנמשחו בקרן, David u-Shlomo she-nimshachu be-keren, David and Shlomo they
were anointed they used a horn right like we saw like a
cornucopia, the horn of plenty, it suggests you know success. So again
we're going to the סימן, siman, so that's רמה קרני. rama karni.
So there kingship was for many years. שאול ויהוא שנמשחו בפך, Shaul
ve-Yehu she-nimshachu be-pach, Shaul and Yehu that they just were using this
cruse and they weren't using a horn, לא נמשכה מלכותן lo nimshacha
malchusan their kingship was very was very foreshortened. Okay, so that's the
end of all that discussion about how you do the משיחה meshicha
and the symbolism and so on. המשוח בשמן המשחה, ha-moshuach be-shemen ha-mishcha,
one anointed with the שמן המשחה shemen ha-mishcha is תנו רבנן משיח
יכול מלך. tano rabbanan mashiach yachol melech. So how do we know
that this משיח mashiach who brings the the special פר, par, how
do we know it's the כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? Maybe since kings
are anointed, maybe it means a
king? So תלמוד לומר talmud lomar כהן. kohen. הכהן המשיח תחתיו. ha-kohen
ha-mashiach tachatav. So it says כהן. kohen. אי כהן יכול מרובה בגדים,
ei kohen yachol merubeh begadim, maybe it's a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
even without the שמן המשחה? shemen ha-mishcha? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar משוח
moshuach משיח. mashiach. אם משיח יכול משיח מלחמה, im mashiach yachol mashiach
milchama, so כהן המשיח, Kohen ha-mashiach, you combine the two, you have
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol with שמן המשחה. shemen ha-mishcha.
One minute says the גמרא, Gemara, there's another כהן kohen who has
שמן המשחה, shemen ha-mishcha, the one who's anointed to lead them into
war. תלמוד לומר והכהן המשיח. talmud lomar ve-ha-kohen ha-mashiach. The extra the
the is there's only one. שאינו משיח על גביו she-eino mashiach al
gabav and there's no one higher than him. He is the head
honcho. מאי משמע mai mashma where do you get that from the
hey? So כדאמר רבא ka-amar Rava היי ירך hai yerech when it
says you shall take the thigh, it means המיומנת שבירך, ha-mimumenet she-beyarech,
the right thigh of the animal. So הכא נמי hacha nami because
ה ha means like the most important. המשיח ha-mashiach means המיומן ha-mimuman
right again you know the bias towards the right, as a lefty
I object, but anyway המיומן שבמשוחים. ha-mimuman she-bimshuchim. Okay, the one that
is the most important of those that are anointed. Okay, so that's
how we know it's the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Go with the
שמן המשחה. Shemen Hamishcha. אמר מר, amar mar, משיח. Mashiach. יכול מלך?
yachol melech? Maybe it means a king? So the גמרא Gemara says,
מלך? Melech? How could this פרשה parsha about the כהן kohen bringing
a פר par be referred to the king? מלך פר הוא דמייתי?
melech par hu d'mayiti? Do you think that the king would bring
an ox? שעיר הוא דמייתי. se'ir hu d'mayiti. He's in the פרשה
parsha of נשיא. Nasi. He brings a goat. So of course it's
not talking about a king. So no, איצטריך, itztrich, you need it.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka datcha amina, I would have thought אשגגות המעשה
יביא שעיר, al shigagot hama'aseh yavi se'ir, when it's a simple sin
by action then he brings the goat. על העלם דבר, al he'elem
davar, but if it's a sin that's also combined with a ruling,
which is the specific conditions of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, maybe
יביא פר, yavi par, maybe he'll bring an ox? קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that this פרשה parsha is not about kings, this
פרשה parsha of a ruling and an action is about a כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, אין בין משוח בשמן המשחה, ein bein mashiach
b'shemen hamishcha, there's no difference between the anointed oil and the מרובה
בבגדים merubeh b'bgadim except for this one difference of the ox. Okay,
מתניתין דלא כרבי מאיר. matnitin d'lo k'Rabbi Meir. Our Mishnah is not
like Rabbi Meir. דאי רבי מאיר, d'ee Rabbi Meir, for if it's
Rabbi Meir, הא תניא: ha tanya: מרובה בבגדים מביא פר. merubeh b'bgadim
mevi par. According to Rabbi Meir, somebody who is just a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol because of the extra clothes does bring a does
bring ה פר ha par על כל המצוות, al kol hamitzvot, דברי
רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what Rabbi Meir says. ולא הודו
לו חכמים, v'lo hodu lo chachamim, and the sages did not agree
with him. Okay, so clearly our משנה mishnah is ruling against Rabbi
Meir. מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר, mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir, what's his reasoning?
דתניא, d'tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא: braita: משיח, Mashiach, the anointed
one. אין לי אלא משוח בשמן המשחה, ein li ela mashiach b'shemen
hamishcha, I only know that that's anointed by the oil, which is
exactly what we say. We limit it to that case. But this
is Rabbi Meir's position. מרובה בבגדים מניין? merubeh b'bgadim minayin? How do
I know, says Rabbi Meir, even if he was just the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol through the clothes? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: הכהן המשיח.
haKohen haMashiach.
Now I don't know how he gets it from הכהן המשיח. haKohen
haMashiach. It's the exact opposite לימוד. limud. Maybe it's a type of
אין מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות. ein mi'ut achar mi'ut ela l'rabot.
You know, the גמרא Gemara that maybe it's just the extra letters
means that we're coming to include an additional person. It doesn't exactly
say how he gets it. Okay, but anyway. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. במאי אוקימתא? b'mai okimta? כרבנן. k'rabanan. So you're saying
our משנה mishnah is like the rabbis who disagree with Rabbi Meir.
אימא סיפא, eima seifa,
let's look at the end of our משנה. mishnah. אין בין כהן
משמש לכהן שעבר, ein bein Kohen meshamesh l'Kohen she'avar, there's no difference
between the current כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who's serving in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and the כהן kohen who substituted for יום כיפור
Yom Kippur but is now no longer serving. אלא פר יום הכיפורים,
ela par Yom HaKippurim, except for who brings the ox that on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that is the currently serving כהן. kohen. ועשירית
האיפה, v'asirit ha'eiphah,
and the מנחה mincha that is brought every day, half in the
morning half in the afternoon, that is by the current acting כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. But all other things can be done even by
this past כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So the גמרא Gemara says, אתיא
כרבי מאיר. atya k'Rabbi Meir. But that's a Rabbi Meir position that
says that says other than those two they're all the same. How
do you know? דתניא, d'tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא: braita: אירע
בו פסול בכהן גדול. eira bo psul b'Kohen Gadol. The כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, something happened to him. He
had seen a seminal emission the night before, he became טמא. tameh.
ומינו כהן אחר תחתיו, v'minu Kohen acher tachtav,
and he was put aside for יום כיפור Yom Kippur and they
had somebody else serve in his place. הראשון חוזר לעבודתו, harishon chozer
l'avodato,
so the first one goes back after יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay,
so so far we're all the same. But now here's the question.
What is the status of the guy who served just for יום
כיפור? Yom Kippur? So this תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says, I'm sorry,
not תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, Rabbi Meir. כל מצוות כהונה עליו, kol
mitzvot kehuna alav, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Meir says
all of the position all of the status of the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is on him, which is basically what our משנה mishnah
says. So the first part of our משנה mishnah that limited the
פר par to משוח mashiach to שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha is not
Rabbi Meir. The second part of our משנה mishnah that says the
כהן kohen that served for יום כיפור Yom Kippur is basically has
almost a full status of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, that is
Rabbi Meir. Because contrast that to the next position. רבי יוסי אומר:
Rabbi Yossi omer: ראשון חוזר לעבודתו, rishon chozer l'avodato, והשני אינו ראוי
לא לכהן גדול ולא לכהן הדיוט. v'hasheni eino ra'uy lo l'Kohen Gadol
v'lo l'Kohen Hedyot. No,
the guy who worked on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, now he can't
go back to any position.
Okay. אמר רבי יוסי: amar Rabbi Yossi: מעשה ביוסף בן אילם מציפורי
ma'aseh b'Yosef ben Eilim miTzipori שארע בו פסול בכהן גדול. she'ara bo
psul b'Kohen Gadol. There
was a story with יוסף Yosef that that there was a problem
with the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. And I'm going to read the
גירסא, girsa, the ג gimmel on the side, which is a better
גירסא, girsa, which says, ומינוהו תחתיו, v'minuhu tachtav, and this יוסף Yosef
was created made the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol for יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. Okay, ובא מעשה, u'va ma'aseh, and then after יום כיפור Yom
Kippur he was put aside. ובא מעשה לפני חכמים u'va ma'aseh lifnei
chachamim ואמרו: v'amru: ראשון חוזר לעבודתו, rishon chozer l'avodato, שני אינו ראוי
לא לכהן גדול ולא לכהן הדיוט. sheni eino ra'uy lo l'Kohen Gadol
v'lo l'Kohen Hedyot.
This יוסף, Yosef, he can no longer serve either as a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol or as a
כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot. כהן גדול משום איבה, Kohen Gadol mishum eivah,
he can't be because that would be, you know, hatred with the
current כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you know, that there's somebody else who
could do everything I'm doing except for two things, right? I'm going
to feel very much that's compromising my unique status. So you can't
let him serve in that capacity. וכהן הדיוט משום מעלין בקודש ואין
מורידין. v'Kohen Hedyot mishum ma'alin bakodesh v'ein moridin. But he can't go
back to being a normal כהן kohen because once he had this
high status you don't depose him and give him a lower role.
So according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, the this guy who served
in the past basically does have does not have any of the
rights of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, maybe also none of the
obligations, but certainly none of the rights. So our משנה mishnah that
says that the כהן kohen who served one day as a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol for except for two exceptions... is pretty much a
full כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position.
But the first line that said that that it's limited for this
פר Par to the כהן Kohen who was anointed, that's a non-רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir position. So how do you fit the two together?
So the גמרא Gemara says,
רישא רבנן וסיפא רבי מאיר? Reisha Rabbanan u-Seifa Rabbi Meir? Did the
beginning of the משנה Mishna be a רבנן Rabbanan position and the
end of the משנה Mishna be a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position?
אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, אין, in, לתירוצא, le-tirutza, רישא רבנן
וסיפא רבי מאיר. Reisha Rabbanan u-Seifa Rabbi Meir. The משנה Mishna is
two separate teachings that were stitched together. Okay, the first one was
a non-רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position, the second one was a רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir position. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, also רב
יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef Amar, now by the way, could I just
say why sometimes the גמרא Gemara says that and you find it
frustrating, but actually, what that is could be doing, it can be
reflecting the edited nature of the משנה, Mishna, and you know, רבי
Rebbe took all these various תנא Tanna sources and wove them together,
stitched them together, I should say. And in our case, it's actually
true, because this thing אין בין כהן שעבר לכהן, Ein bein Kohen
She-avar l'kohen, you know, what is it, אין בין, Ein bein, what's
the language in the
משנה, Mishna, אין בין כהן המשוח, Ein bein Kohen HaMashiach, oh actually
I take that back, אין בין כהן המשמש לכהן שעבר אלא פר
יום הכפורים. Ein bein Kohen HaMeshammesh l'kohen She-avar ela Par Yom HaKippurim.
That אין בין, Ein bein, that's from מגילה, Megilla, but actually I
take it back because the first אין בין Ein bein is from
that same from that same source: אין בין כהן המשיח אלא פר
הבא על כל המצות. Ein bein Kohen HaMashiach ela Par HaBa al
kol HaMitzvos. So that actually isn't stitched together. That actually does seem
to be one coherent unit. So given that those are two אין
בין, Ein beins, it actually is hard to say that they're different
תנאים. Tanaim. But that's the first answer. Yeah, two different opinions that
they were stitched together.
אמר Amar so רב יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef Amar, רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says no, I don't want to just say it was two
things that don't work together that happened to be put side by
side. רבי, Rebbe, it's רבי's Rebbe own position. ונסיב לה אליבא דתנאי.
Ve-nasiv lei aliba d'tannai. He likes the non-רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position
in the first issue, that it's limited to the oil, and he
likes the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position in the second issue, that
a past כהן גדול Kohen Gadol pretty much remains a full כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, so it's not two different opinions that were
stitched together, it's the position of
רבי Rebbe that's a hybrid position. רבא אמר רבי שמעון היא. Rava
amar Rabbi Shimon hi. It's similar to the answer that it's רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir who holds these two different positions, it's רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon who holds these two different positions. וסבר לה כרבי מאיר
בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא. Ve-savar lei ke-Rabbi Meir be-chada u-palig alei be-chada.
And he holds like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in one case, in
the case about a past כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is like a
full כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and he holds like against רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that in case of the special קרבן, Korban, that is
limited to the one who is anointed with the שמן המשחה. Shemen
HaMishcha. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, where do you
know that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds these two positions? דברים שבין
כהן גדול לכהן הדיוט. Devarim she-bein Kohen Gadol le-kohen hedyot. The differences,
what are the differences between a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and a
כהן הדיוט? Kohen Hedyot? אלו הן, Elu hein, are the following. Here's
a nice list of all the differences. פר הבא על כל המצות,
Par HaBa al kol HaMitzvos, what קרבן Korban you bring when you
sin, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings the special ox, and it
requires a פסק Psak as well. ופר יום הכפורים, U-par Yom HaKippurim,
there's a special ox that's brought on יום כפור Yom Kippur that
is not only done by the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, but it
actually is the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol קרבן, Korban, it's his money
that pays for that ox. ועשירית האיפה, Va-asiris ha-eifah, and the tenth
of the ephah, which also is a מנחה Mincha of his that
is brought every day, half in the morning, half in the afternoon.
ולא פורע ולא פורם. Ve-lo pore'a ve-lo porem. When he suffers an
immediate death in the family, he does not do normal signs of
mourning, he does not let his hair grow wild, he does not
rend his clothes. אבל הוא פורם מלמטה. Aval hu porem milimata. He
does do a tearing at the bottom of his garment. ונדבר Ve-nadabeir
we'll talk about that in a minute. והדיוט מלמעלה. Ve-hedyot milimalah. But
a normal כהן Kohen does it at the top of the garment,
by the neck. אין מטמא לקרובים. Ein mitamei le-krovim. Again, when he
suffers an immediate loss he cannot become טמא tamei even if mother
and a father or a son and a daughter. ומוזהר על הבתולה.
U-muzhar al habesulah. He can't marry a woman who is not a
virgin. Actually it's funny the phrase מוזהר muzhar because it's a מצוה
Mitzvah to marry a virgin, it's not a negative prohibition against it.
ואסור באלמנה, Ve-asur be-almanah, he can't marry a widow, and a normal
כהן Kohen can marry a widow, just not a גרושה. Grushah. ומחזיר
את הרוצח. U-machazir es harotze'ach. When he dies the murderer comes back
from the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. ומקריב אונן. U-makriv onen. When on
the day that he suffered a death, he can he can still
continue doing bringing קרבנות Korbanot in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ואינו
אוכל, Ve-eino ochel, but he can't eat. This week's פרשה, Parsha, האכלתי
חטאת היום הייטב בעיני ה', He-achalti Chatas Hayom Hayita Be'einai Hashem, right,
when אהרן Aharon suffers the loss and he does not eat the
קרבן חטאת. Korban Chatas. So a כהן Kohen who is an אונן,
onen, even though he is מקריב makriv when he is an אונן,
onen, brings the קרבן, Korban, he cannot eat from the קרבן. Korban.
So go ahead and look at רש"י Rashi on the פסוק Pasuk
of when אהרן Aharon says האכלתי חטאת היום הייטב בעיני ה', He-achalti
Chatas Hayom Hayita Be'einai Hashem, it's exactly tied in to this הלכה.
Halacha. ואינו חולק, Ve-eino cholek,
and he does not, you know, take a portion of the sacrifice
because I mean, whatever, there's a question about that גירסא, girsa, we'll
skip that for now. מקריב חלק בראש ונוטל חלק בראש. Makriv chelek
berosh venoteil chelek berosh. Under normal cases, not in an אונן onen
situation,
he gets to decide, "Hey, I'm, you know, jump in front of
the line, I'm going to bring this קרבן," Korban, and he also
gets to say, "I'm taking my first dibs on the meat or
whatever from the קרבנות." Korbanos. ומשמש בשמונה כלים. U-meshammesh bishmonah keilim. He
wears the eight vestments, and a normal כהן Kohen just wears four.
וכל עבודת יום הכיפורים נכשרה בו, vechol avodat Yom HaKippurim nichsharah bo,
he has to be the one doing the עבודה avodah of יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, even not his עת. et. ופוטר טומאת מקדש וקדשיו,
upoter tumat mikdash vekodashav,
and he does not bring a קרבן korban for טומאת מקדש וקדשיו
tumat mikdash vekodashav that we learned before, that's based on a certain
idea since his קרבן korban on יום כיפור Yom Kippur is different
or whatever, he doesn't bring a קרבן korban if for טומאת מקדש.
tumat mikdash. וכולן נוהגין במרובה בגדים, vechulan nohegin bimruveh begadim,
all of these apply to a כהן kohen who is not anointed
with the שמן המשחה, shemen hamishcha, is a כהן גדול kohen gadol
just for wearing the extra vestments, חוץ מפר המביא על כל המצוות,
chutz mipara mevi'ah al kol hamitzvot, except for the ox. So that's
the first position of our משנה, mishnah, that somebody who is a
כהן גדול kohen gadol without the oil does not bring the ox.
וכולן נוהגין במשיח שעבר, vechulan nohegin bimshiach she'avar, and they all apply
to a past כהן גדול, kohen gadol, חוץ מפר יום הכיפורים ועשירית
האיפה, chutz mipara Yom HaKippurim ve'asirit haeifah, except for the ox of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the tenth of the איפה. eifah. So
that is the second part of our משנה, mishnah, right? That is
the part that the past כהן גדול kohen gadol has the full
status of a כהן גדול kohen gadol with except for these two
parts. So the exact two positions of the משנה mishnah which you
said one is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and one isn't, here this
ברייתא beraita holds exactly of the both positions of the משנה mishnah
that the פר par for the כהן גדול kohen gadol is limited
to the one who's anointed with the oil, and a past כהן
גדול kohen gadol except for two exceptions has the same status as
an acting כהן גדול. kohen gadol. וכולן אינן נוהגין אלא במשיח מלחמה,
vechulan einam nohegin ela bemshiach milchama, and none of these special statuses
apply to the כהן kohen for who's anointed for war, חוץ מחמישה
דברים האמורים בפרשה, chutz mechamesh devarim ha'amurim baparsha, except for the five
things said in the beginning of אמור: Emor: לא פורע ולא פורם
ואינו מטמא לקרובים ומצווה על הבתולה ואסור על האלמנה. lo poreiah velo
porem ve'eino mitamei likrovim umetzuvah al habetulah ve'asur al ha'almanah. Doesn't do
the signs of mourning, does not become טמא tamei to relatives, has
to marry a בתולה betulah and can't marry an אלמנה. almanah. Anyway,
ומחזיר את הרוצח, umachazir et harotzeach, and brings back the רוצח. rotzeach.
That sounds to me like six. Oh, so this is and the
sixth one is a debate.
ומחזיר את הרוצח דברי רבי יהודה וחכמים אומרים אינו מחזיר. umachazir et
harotzeach divrei Rabbi Yehuda vechachamim omrim eino machazir. Fine. So that's the
משיח מלחמה. mashuach milchama. Anyway, here you have a ברייתא beraita that
is exactly those two positions in the משנה, mishnah, one like רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, one not like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So we
said ah, it's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So the גמרא Gemara says
look, you show me a ברייתא beraita that holds just like our
משנה, mishnah, but how do you know it's רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
So the גמרא Gemara says והאי ממאי דרבי שמעון היא, vehai mimai
deRabbi Shimon hi, how do you know it's רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
אמר רב פפא מאן שמעת ליה דאמר פוטר טומאת מקדש וקדשיו רבי
שמעון. amar Rav Pappa man shami'at leh de'amar potter tumat mikdash vekodashav
Rabbi Shimon. Because
one of the things it says that a כהן גדול kohen gadol
is exempt from טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash, from the קרבן עולה ויורד.
korban oleh veyored. Okay, but if you remember, that was a teaching
that was taught a few דפים dappim ago in the name of
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So here you have a ברייתא beraita that
has exactly those two positions and we can identify it as a
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon ברייתא, beraita, so this is רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. It's not yes רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it's not not רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, let's just finish
up to the משנה. mishnah. חוץ מחמישה דברים האמורים בפרשה, chutz mechamesh
devarim ha'amurim baparsha, the משיח מלחמה, mashuach milchama, the only thing that
applies to him are the five things at the beginning of פרשת
אמור. Parshat Emor. מנא הני מילי, minani hani mili, where do you
know this from? תנו רבנן והכהן הגדול מאחיו זה כהן גדול אשר
יוצק על ראשו שמן המשחה זה משיח מלחמה. tano rabbanan vehakohen hagadol
me'echav zeh kohen gadol asher yutzak al rosho shemen hamishcha zeh mashuach
milchama. So the יוצק על ראשו yutzak al rosho
rather than reading it as limiting only to the כהן גדול kohen
gadol with oil, we read it as expanding. Even somebody who's not
the כהן גדול kohen gadol but has a special status of a
כהן kohen because of the oil. Who is that? That's the כהן
kohen who's anointed for war. ומילא את ידו ללבש את הבגדים זה
מרובה בגדים. umilei et yado lilbosh et habegadim zeh meruveh begadim. The
way we know to read it expansive is because of this last
phrase. The last phrase says he wears the special vestments. So that
includes a כהן גדול kohen gadol who's not anointed. So once you're
including a כהן גדול kohen gadol who's not anointed, why are you
mentioning anointing? To include the משיח מלחמה. mashuach milchama. על כולן הוא
אומר, al kulan hu omer, and now that's how it starts, so
for all these three special כהנים, kohanim, כהן גדול kohen gadol with
the oil, without the oil, and משיח מלחמה, mashuach milchama, it says:
על כולן הוא אומר ראשו לא יפרע ובגדיו לא יפרום ועל כל
נפשות מת לא יבוא לאביו ולאמו לא יטמא, al kulan hu omer
rosho lo yifra uvegadav lo yifrom ve'al kol nafshot met lo yavo
le'aviv ule'imo lo yitama, etc., etc. All the things of the special
things of the פרשה parsha that apply to a כהן גדול kohen
gadol apply also to the משיח מלחמה. mashuach milchama. יכול יהיו כולן
מקריבים אוננים, yachol yehu chulam makrivim onenim,
maybe all of them can bring so you know if the משיח
מלחמה mashuach milchama doesn't become טמא tamei to an immediate relative, so
maybe he stays in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and he can
even continue to be to bring קרבנות. korbanot. תלמוד לומר כי נזר
שמן משחת אלוהיו עליו. talmud lomar kinezer shemen mishchat elohav alav. When
it says ומן המקדש לא יצא, umin hamikdash lo yetze,
don't exit the מקדש mikdash when an immediate relative dies, so not
only is it saying don't become טמא, tamei, it already said that,
לאביו ולאמו לא יטמא, le'aviv ule'imo lo yitama, so don't exit the
מקדש mikdash is saying continue doing the עבודה avodah even though you
just lost a father or or mother or a son or a
daughter. So that, when it says continue doing the עבודה avodah it
says because God's anointing oil is on you, okay, עליו ולא על
חבירו, alav velo al chaviro, on you, not on the person similar
to you. So it's only apply it doesn't need the oil but
it only applies to the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, only so even
though a משיח מלחמה mashuach milchama does not become טמא, tamei, he
does not have the right to continue doing the עבודה. avodah. That's
limited to the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Okay, ואחר שחילקו הכתוב יכול
לא יהא מצווה על הבתולה, ve'achar shechilko hakatuv yachol lo yehei metzuvah
al habetulah, once now
the the
there's a distinction in terms of being מקריב אונן, makriv onen, so
maybe now he also you know because afterwards the next פסוק pasuk
says והוא אשה בבתוליה יקח, vehu ishah bivtulei yikach, marry a virgin.
That's the next פסוק. pasuk. So since in the previous פסוק pasuk
we excluded... the משיח מלחמה mashiach milchama because we said that the
משיח מלחמה mashiach milchama does not continue working in the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, maybe the next פסוק pasuk when it says marry a
virgin is no longer talking about the משיח מלחמה. mashiach milchama. Okay,
so it says אחר שחלק הכתוב achar shechilak hakatuv יכול לא יהא
מצווה על הבתולה, yachol lo yehei mitzuve al habesulah,
maybe he's not obligated to marry the בתולה, besulah, תלמוד לומר והוא.
talmud lomar v'hu. והוא אשה בבתוליה יקח, v'hu isha b'visuleha yikach,
which is the next פסוק. pasuk. The extra ו vov is coming
to say him and someone else. So the extra ו vov brings
back in the משיח מלחמה. mashiach milchama. So you get it? The
opening פסוקים pesukim are talking about all of them and it says,
you know, don't become טמא tamei to relatives, don't do the signs
of mourning, don't leave the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because you have
the sort of—you're the anointed of God. So that last פסוק, pasuk,
don't leave the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you're the anointed of God,
we read you but not the משיח מלחמה. mashiach milchama. And then
the next פסוק pasuk says והוא אשה בבתוליה יקח. v'hu isha b'visuleha
yikach. So the ו vov of והוא v'hu brings back the משיח
מלחמה. mashiach milchama. And the משיח מלחמה mashiach milchama also can only
marry a virgin. Okay, כתנאי. kitnaei. This issue is a debate of
תנאים. tannaim. והוא אשה בבתוליה יקח v'hu isha b'visuleha yikach אחר שחלק
הכתוב ריבה דברי רבי ישמעאל. achar shechilak hakatuv riba divrei Rabbi Yishmael.
After the פסוק pasuk excluded him, it went back and included him
that even a משיח מלחמה mashiach milchama has to marry a virgin.
רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva omer אין לי אלא שעבר—no, ein li
ela she'avar משיח מלחמה mashiach milchama remains excluded. So what's the extra
והוא? v'hu? אין לי אלא שעבר מחמת קריא מחמת מום מנין ein
li ela she'avar machmas kirya machmas mum minayin?
I only know that if somebody was deposed from a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol because of, like, you know, that he had a seminal
emission, he retains the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol status. How do I
know somebody who was removed from the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol because
he had some blemish retains the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol status and
has to only marry a virgin and not marry a widow? תלמוד
לומר והוא. talmud lomar v'hu. So for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the
ו vov is including a version of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
but it is not including the משיח מלחמה. mashiach milchama. And we
end with one final question. בעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן, ba'i minei
Rava meiRav Nachman, רבא Rava asked רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, משיח שנצטרע
מהו באלמנה mashiach shenitzara mahu b'almanah?
If a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol had צרעת tzara'as and he can
no longer serve as a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol with the צרעת,
tzara'as, can he now marry an אלמנה? almanah? Okay, I mean, what
would happen when the צרעת tzara'as goes away? I don't know. מדחא
דחי—does midcha dachi the status of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol completely
push the category of אלמנה almanah away from him, או מיפטר פטר—does
o miptar patar it mean it's like—it's an exemption, right now it's
preventing him from marrying an אלמנה, almanah, but it's not seen as
a permanent status? Okay, and if it's only seen as a temporary
exemption, when he's no longer serving as a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
he would once again be permitted.
לא הוה בידיה—he lo hava beyadei didn't know the answer. זימנין דהוה
יתיב רב פפא וקמיבעיא ליה—there zimnin dehavah yasiv Rav Papa vekamibaia lei
was times that רב פפא Rav Papa was sitting and asking. אמר
ליה הונא בריה דרב נחמן לרב פפא. amar lei Huna brei deRav
Nachman leRav Papa. So רב פפא Rav Papa was sort of raising
this question, and הונא, Huna, the son of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
said to רב פפא, Rav Papa, תנינא—we tenina learned it from a
ברייתא. beraisa. אין לי אלא שעבר מחמת קריא ועבר מחמת מום מנין
ein li ela she'avar machmas kirya ve'avar machmas mum minayin? How do
you know a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol even if he was, you
know, sort of put out of his job because of a blemish,
that he still has the same הלכות halachos that apply to him,
he still can only marry a בתולה, besulah, etc.? תלמוד לומר והוא.
talmud lomar v'hu. So if you see that a blemish, he still
retains the status of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol for the marriage
laws, then the same would be true if it's צרעת. tzara'as. So
he said it's clear in the ברייתא. beraisa. רב פפא קם נשקיה
ברישיה ויהיב ליה ברתיה. Rav Papa kam nashkeih berisheih veyahiv lei barteih.
רב פפא Rav Papa got up, kissed him on his head,
and married his daughter to him. So since we're talking about marriage,
I guess. Anyway, nobody asked the daughter what she thought. All right,
we will end with this for today.